the ayedee little devil the Bohannon
you're
okay well let's just wait a bit
some people are I'm okay well welcome to
the seminar presentation about car
deformation my name is Johanna Strela
and I'm going to show a small thing from
the organizer how many of you here came
by a car okay there are some okay good
because there is some problem with the
parking maybe you have seen so I think
you should keep in mind that you
shouldn't park to those yellow areas in
the region because there has been some
problems in previous years so this is
some material captured last year so
those yellow regions they are not to be
recommended but seriously here is some
examples of core deformation in use so
it's deformation just means that the
cars deform and formed their shape after
collision or crash so it is basically a
short introduction to the presentation I
will show a more more clips a bit later
that's so I did this this is actually
part of my thesis work at Lin shopping
University and I did it for bugbear
entertainment here in Finland and then
shopping is in Sweden if you didn't know
so the basic outline of the presentation
follows pretty much every academic work
we have introduction theory and
implementation and then some conclusions
this is maybe a bit theory heavy I try
to give it not too much but for starters
the deformation is defined in the
Webster well I mean American Heritage
Dictionary in this way so deformation is
an alteration of shape as high pressure
or stress so here in core games usually
the deformation occurs in crises and
they are usually fun to watch but not so
fun to be in so the basic deformation
thing is based on all the research is
based on Hookes law Hookes law is pretty
simple approximation and it just States
study how the amount of deformation is
linearly in linear relationship to the
amount of stress applied so in many
materials this approximation goes pretty
well for elastic materials justice you
could see robberies so when you release
the stress also the deformation part it
Rizza
returns to its original position but for
many materials metal and as in course
again when enough stress is applied it
reaches a plastic region which means
that when you bend enough metal it
doesn't return to original position
anymore so that's what especially in car
games we want to keep those nice bumps
and things after the crash and when you
apply even more force the fracture will
occur so the doors ripped away and
things like that in games
there has been some deformation
destruction derby was one of the
pioneering games in this area 1995
already they had some some kind of
simple deformation and there are many
different damage systems how to do this
deformation and destruction derby and
many of our own games they use sort of
artist defined mesh so artist actually
makes the wreck of a car and then when
the collision occurs we just morph
towards that brick so basically it looks
very nice an artist can define really
exotic shapes for the car but in actual
world when you cross the bomber for
example somewhere usually it doesn't
always end up being in the same way when
you keep on doing it so more dynamic way
was needed so that's why this thesis
about also finite element analysis has
been and will be more useful in later
but it's pretty intense I'll go cool a
bit later with about Bach /
entertainment we have been doing car
games since year 2000 and the engine
where this was my research was
implemented in it it's multi-platform
game engine also the physics and
destruction has been quite important to
our games those of you who are not
familiar with pop param I'll go show a
small trailer from our latest game which
is due to appear also on PC maybe today
even I'm not sure when it's coming out
well there are of course some flying
guys but never mind those I try to focus
on the car came car crashes so in this
kind of games it's pretty important to
have crises that are beautiful and nice
to watch and you don't have to
experience those in real life so it's
that's not hurt to do it in simulation
and not with your own course
so there are many cars see you see here
you really need to have some very
efficient algorithms to do it and that's
the physics in games in general so
usually well almost in every game if you
don't think those who like ten years ago
does one screen and then you move there
usually they are in real time so you
don't you don't have the time to do
calculations in Devon indefinitely so
real time performance is needed
Luc's is usually more preferred to
accuracy so when it looks good enough
it's good enough you're done go to
physics and physics labs and do this is
it exactly the same way than the real
call would be but if it looks good it's
good
and also the separation between visual
and physical damage is important and
this means that when for example the car
gets a very great hit from the side the
tires would move somewhere and you would
still like the player to be able to
drive it a car even though in real world
it would not be possible so in that
sense you would like to see it visually
but you would not want to give it in the
real physics of the game so you know
it's nice to have them separated about
different methods used for deformation
in the gaming industry and elsewhere as
well mastering systems they have been
used for a closed and some rigid body
simulation one one very good paper was
released by Jacobson and it's available
online and there is lots of C code and
everything so go have fun you can create
closed and rigid body simulation very
easily his idea is with this yeah I
guess everybody considers in those
corners there are toast
they are control particles which contain
some information about the structure
they can be mass or they can be some
there can be some constraints between
the two points for example in the rigid
body case there is constraint of the
distance so basically when you do the
physics simulation with the control
points then you in each iteration step
you check the distance between the
points and try to force it so that's the
rigid body simulation basically in the
simple case and he's one of the greatest
things in my opinion in his paper are
these integration things you maybe know
from basic high school things that you
can calculate the next position in
animation in this simple formula so you
have the velocity calculated with the
acceleration and time and then you use
that to determine the next time step in
games this is maybe not always stable
because the velocity can sometimes an
acceleration may give pretty weird
values so he used this kind of bullet in
the creation instead so here there is no
velocity at all but we determined the
next position using the previous
position so this is one of the greatest
things he showed in this article and the
mass spring system is using that they
are stable so you cannot get any dirt
results and then there is this freeform
deformation it's used in modeling
packages 3dmax and those usually give
you a shape which you can just bend and
then it deforms to shape inside the
lattice so it was this sarahburke you I
will develop a method to this containing
like this kind of control lattice so you
have the mesh or
the 3d object you put inside lattice and
then you modify the lattice and using
the formula then you actually modify the
mesh inside so you always do the physics
simulation on this more simple structure
and well I won't go too much into
details about freeform deformation but
basically it's using this kind of burns
then blending functions this B's here
are just B spline functions so you could
just take these control points and then
calculate the best piece flying you need
every three directions and then use that
kind of formula to determine the final
position for the mesh vertices or
whatever you want to transform then
what's becoming more and more popular at
least LucasArts is using their methods
and many other people are using their
own for toca racing race driver and
those are claiming to be using finite
element analysis so it's it's a very
very good method and it's used in real
car industry to calculate stress forces
and actually it was developed for
airplane wings in NASA so like to find
out what kind of stress is in which part
of the wings and which need to be
stronger and so so basically it takes
the volume of object and then fills it
with those finite elements well usually
tetrahedrons are used but you can use
cubes or whatever and then again there
artist control particles which contain
some information about the volume itself
like mass again and other things which
are then combined to one matrix for it's
the needs of this self and then they are
all all these matrices are combined to a
huge matrix which need to be solved in
each iteration step so it's
it's quite intense on computation
there's this you really cannot cheat in
this way you have to solve the whole
huge matrix for the whole system then
there are mesh three methods which are
the ones I ended up using with they are
they do not take into consideration
about the connectivity at all so you
just have a group of particles you did a
physics simulation on those and then you
do this least squares to find out the
actual positions and there are I will go
a bit more into detail about that but
the paper was published four years ago
by Matthias Mueller and it's called this
merciless deformation based on shape
matching you can see it online and give
it to the demo version of some editor so
basically we have this original state in
that square there and then you apply
physics simulation wind or car crash or
whatever you move the particles and then
you use least squares to draw those
points toward the original shape so they
will seem to be affecting nicely
rigidbody simulation is very easy to do
with this you just actually forced them
to be in there and you get the rotation
correct so comparing these methods and
they all share the concept of control
particles you which contain the
information about the strength how much
how easily the material paints or mass
or whatever then the physics simulation
operates only on those control particles
and it then some formulas used to move
the actual object mesh so that's it the
common things but then there are issues
for the mass-spring system it's very
difficult to construct at least
automatically construct my spring
network which would suit for a complex
object such a such as a car you have to
do pull strings in many directions to
get the shape to be at least somehow
formable and then with the freeform
deformation two lattices also limited in
form because you want to be able to draw
those these points so you wear weird
shapes are not easily done with that
then with the finite element analysis
the most problem is the computation it
requires pretty much computational power
and at least so far no public methods
has been released doing that in real
time but many some companies are making
some money with their methods so mr.
shape matching it tells possibility for
interpenetration so because there is no
connectivity information kept you only
do the simulation with particles in some
cases there is a slight chance of
interpret interpret III is a math
interpretation okay then also increasing
the decree of the method will increase
the storage and computation because you
can do it linearly using three by three
matrices but then you can also increase
include pending and those properties
then it would be nine point nine
matrices you have to store a huge amount
the theory for this which I selected was
this mess with shape matching and it's
pretty efficient with the mathematics
you can do that calculation in GPU or
you can multi-threaded because they are
independent of each other so you can do
the calculations very efficiently it
pretty stable at least in the sense that
we are also using similar in the
creation themes as I mentioned from
chalk option and then it's flexible and
the pre-processing is basically
constructing a cell crate for object
well here in the upper right hand corner
it's constructing those cubes just and
puts mesh inside the shape can be
anything and those cubes just need to be
connected somehow
then it's the plasticity case plus this
it was the part of the wear elasticity
and so the plasticity is that case where
the metal gives it form so it's also
considered already in the original paper
I referred to so this is the
implementation pipeline pretty much the
control particles are created created in
the beginning so just basically doing
that salting and it's in its corner of
this whole thing there is a control
particle then you apply physics to those
particles you can do the color crisis or
whatever then you for each of those
cells you need to find optimal
transformation and it's the first
formula here is and the least squares
and this is the salt form so basically
you just find the optimal matrix using
the least squares and you can you can
use that matrix to apply that matrix to
vertices or normal so you can transfer
things inside those cells so the paper
also separated rotational and linear
part so you can do here is the linear
transformation in the over there on the
left hand side there is only linear
transformation applied to that cube and
then rotation on the right hand side
rotation and linear okay so those are
separated in the algorithm so using
polar decomposition method you can do
that I have a link to that in the end of
presentation so I will it will show you
a paper Pike and Schumaker which shows
you how to do the polar decomposition
it's one of the most intense mathematics
in the method so it's good to have that
implemented well then this matrix is
well as I said it's the final matrix is
used to transform the final matrices and
normals this is the nice state diagram
maybe I won't go through it but it's
well yeah maybe I won't go through it
but the simulation is pretty simple
anyway some additional modifications to
the algorithm I did was to add a little
bit to the plasticity because the
original paper it only covers plasticity
using linear part it doesn't consider
the rotation at all so you end up if you
have this kind of form and then you say
that no you can start to deform when you
are only having linear transformations
then you end up having this kind of
things because they cannot contain any
rotation so I just added the rotation
thing there and then you get nicer
bending there also when you are doing
the rotation there are some problems
with that because you have to
interpolate between the control
particles but it's actually Oh actually
nice in course because you get those
nice cracks in between you can see in
the demo later then to do this rotation
you just have to apply the matrices you
have to recalculate the centers of
masses for the
so it's no big deal then you can
increase the stiffness by iterating and
there is a problem when you increase the
size of those cells you increase like we
have 150 cells now in one core so when
you add more and more cells the
stiffness loses because it interpolates
between so things will get more squiggly
so you can fix it or improve it by
iterating a few times of course you
don't want to do that too much in real
time simulation again you can improve it
and nice thing to know is that when
you're transforming normals using the
same matrices you have to multiply not
with actual a matrix but with transpose
of the inverse of the matrix just not so
when I started in doing this thesis so I
did first some simple editor to get some
isolated testing in environment so I
wouldn't have to mess around with the
game engine I did a simple editor where
you can pretty much test everything do
you need to do with this method and I
could also just other methods like those
mass-spring systems and everything in
this map and see how they compare to
each other so interface in game engine
there were some additional stuff I had
to do of course morals usually consists
of several messages and then inside the
core you have some objects which are
more stiff like the engine for example
you don't want it to bend in the same
way than the doors or roof is more it's
not as stiff as the doors and so on so I
have to do some things to allow that
so basically it's just having some
controls for artists to specify those
properties for those control points of
course I added some visuals tools and
optimizing and everything here is a
video clip of things working somehow at
least it's our nice testing environment
so I showed you some clips earlier so
here is everything is deformed nothing
is done by graphic artist only the
textured things but you can see pretty
intense deformation for for the car only
using this method let's see here a bit
later you can see there I'm showing the
actual cell cluster so you can see Oh
you don't usually see this kind of
course in car games because you cannot
really do it but this is the control
shape the blue one and then the red ones
are the collision spheres
so now again again the cell structure
each of them having their own matrices
and then the coalition shape has to be
deformed as well so you just applied the
same matrix to the sphere sphere sphere
positions as well and I had some still
images showing the same thing
so as concluding save matching is it's
very efficient there is lots of room for
optimizing end it's pretty scalable you
can do it for other things 10 cores as
well
then with using the parameter at
adjusting like you can adjust the
stiffness and those things you can get
pretty good results even even though
it's not finite element is still but you
can get pretty nice results you can
actually separate some parts like the
having the engine more stiff those
things and then for the future work of
course this kind of deformation fracture
fluid you can try to apply similar
things there
I didn't implement fracture yet because
we have pretty similar system already in
use well you have to see that later then
the future seems to go everybody seems
to be more and more interested in finite
element analysis but in my opinion this
shape matching might be just enough and
it's much more lightweight so but we've
all seen where it goes that's the end
thanks for listening
so if you have some questions I will try
to answer them yes
oh yeah the question was does it affect
car course
you mean towards the air or yeah so the
question was does it affect physically
to the car when it's deformed well as I
said in the beginning of the
presentation to some degree we try to
keep it separated from the and the
visual damage and the physical damage
because then we can have better control
because we always want that the player
is able to try with the car to some
degree but already there are some
because it's very easy to calculate from
these cells that how much they are
deformed so according to that you can
adjust you can even see if the tall
tires are in right place to drop them
off or something so in that sense yes
and no because we want to control it
separate a little bit but you could do
it all already a bit of physical
appearances this transforming those
collisions fears it already affects when
you have deformed a banana shaped
current and you drop it somewhere it
will squeak yeah any other questions
okay it's not I had some few performance
and here are some links and well I can
if you're interested in